hello folks and welcome to hollow talk
for the week of April 26 1998 this is
Frank defreitis
in an effort to try and keep Hollow talk
as diverse as possible this week our
show will take a look into the fields of
laser light shows and my guest is L
Michael Roberts of Burlington Canada and
Laser FX International
Mr Roberts if you are not already aware
has been designing creating and
Performing laser light shows since 1976.
and is the person who developed the
original laser light show dance party
Concepts back in 1978 which is now a
standard
at nightclubs and Raves
throughout the world
he's performed laser light shows for
major corporations toured
internationally with rock bands and has
done fireworks spectaculars and provided
Motion Picture special effects
is even performed for her majesty Queen
Elizabeth II
oh Michael Roberts is the author of
laser FX which is considered by many to
be the Bible
of laser light share manuals
along with a host of other items and
activities including a quarterly
newsletter and an incredible website
devoted to the industry
we'll be talking with Mr Roberts in just
a moment who will attempt to give
comprehensive answers to my obviously
amateur questions concerning laser light
shows but first
few items
the webcam
I'm going to try and get this put
together over the weekend and hope to
have the first broadcast this Thursday
night
you'll be able to see into the studio as
I put the show together
now you'll not be able to hear a live
broadcast at the moment
as I cannot broadcast live audio yet but
you will be able to call into the studio
on a toll-free number and get on the
show
you can call in with your holography
questions and or just call in to say
hello and that you listen to the show so
come to the live webcam page Thursday
night April 30th
11 pm Eastern Time
you'll see the live webcam link on the
left side of the holotalk page this will
be every week from now on I also have a
studio link where you can see pictures
from the studio now you'll notice that
the whole talk page has been redesigned
with additional Pages added so check out
these new pages while you're here
okay on to the interview with L Michael
Roberts of the you run to approximately
a half hour I'm not going to come back
on after the interview so once again I
will say thank you for tuning in and if
you would like to get on the new
holotalk listeners guide email list
click on the link for updates and guests
which you will also find on the left
hand side of the page
okay on to L Michael Roberts see you
next week and hopefully Thursday night
with the live webcam take care
hello everyone I'm speaking with L
Michael Roberts who's with the laser FX
International Michael welcome to the
show well thank you very much we're
going to get some information from him
on a convention that's coming up among
other things that we're going to speak
about tonight but why don't we go right
in with the laser FX 98 convention
that's happening May 16th to 18th can
you tell us a little about it sure this
is our fourth annual laser FX event we
hold them in Burlington Ontario
part of the reason for that is that
audience scanning European style
audience scanning laser shows are legal
in Canada and audience scanning is not
legal in the US oh I see the conference
is a three-day event on Saturday we have
a number of uh committee meetings the
international laser display Association
will be holding their technical
committee meeting there'll be other
groups meeting we have an open house on
Saturday night Sunday is a trade show
most of the day Sunday evening is the
big event uh it's a the Brewster awards
banquet we have a Sumptuous buffet
dinner and then everyone sits down to
look at laser shows which are played
back from ADOT tape using a full color
laser system with fiber optic remote
beam heads and everyone who's in the
room gets a ballot and gets to vote on
what they consider to be the best laser
show that they saw that evening and the
winner is awarded with Fame and the
lovely lovely uh award to put on their
show are the winners awarded that night
oh well yes we announced the winners
immediately but obviously we can't give
out the awards immediately because we
don't uh
with all those lasers you can't do any
laser engraving on the spot huh no the
lasers are all visible and typically for
laser Engravings you want to use CO2
lasers then the Monday is the seminar
day and uh on that day we have a number
of seminars on various topics we have a
business issues uh Roundtable with a
number of successful laserists we have
what's new technical session in which
people with new goods and Equipment will
discuss the technical working how they
operate and what makes them better than
other products could you explain to the
listeners and myself as well I'm not
sure what audience scanning means what
is that uh audience scanning is where
the laser beam is projected directly
onto the people in
oh sort of like a spread of light that
goes up and down or sideways or
something correct well there are many
different forms of audio scanning
effects there's sheets there's ways
there's fans
fashion shows and things like the models
walk down through the uh two tunnels
typically you see this mostly outside
the USA it's not in the USA at all
except perhaps it's an underground and
illegal Raves using low power lasers
because it is illegal to scan onto the
well it's not illegal it's just
technically extremely complex requires a
lot of safeguards a lot of paperwork in
order to scan onto the audience in the
United States but in Europe there are
companies that have laser systems as
powerful as 57 Watts that scan directly
onto the audience now obviously the
audience is not standing a few feet away
yes they're usually on the other side of
a lake or in a large public area so the
what we have to look at is energy
density now one of the things we're
doing this year because there's been a
certain amount of controversy about uh
audience scanning is having a special
audience scanning workshop at the uh
on seminar day at Laser FX and that is
uh demonstrate to people what is a good
way and a bad way to do things for
example if you were projecting a square
tunnel you would want to be sure that
the corners were not any brighter than
any other part because that causes a
hazard in terms of of the energy because
there's more energy than in the corners
than there is in the rest of the beam
yeah sometimes you see actual dots in
the corner that's because it's being
scanned more than once in that area is
that correct that's right that's because
usually there are a number of points in
that corner that uh that are there
designed to hold the squareness of the
beam in place as it changes Direction
often called anchor points from what I
understand there's a Hot Topic in Las
Vegas right now with actually between
the laser light show people and the
airport authorities there are you aware
of this oh yes this has been a very hot
issue in the industry and continues to
be a heart issue in the industry life is
in that airspace how this came about is
that a number of Las Vegas hotels
installed very large laser shows to
shoot beams of light into
the part of attracting people to their
facilities
and in part this year's day new
technology called the yag laser which is
an infrared laser that's been frequency
doubled to 532 nanometers the 532
spectral line is very very close to the
peak sensitivity of the human eye so for
example a 10 watt yag laser would appear
as bright to the human eye as a 30 or 35
watt argon laser so some of these places
installed 30 and 40 watt and some even
brighter than that and multiple of these
lasers and shot them out into the night
sky and they did it all in compliance
with existing regulations
but a number of Pilots got flashed as
they were coming into land and there's a
perception amongst a lot of people that
lasers sort of like death Rays yes and
that if you touch it your face will melt
like the guy in in Raiders of the Lost
Ark but in actual fact the real danger
is that you get momentary flash
blindness in other words it's very
similar to the effect of having your
photograph taken at a dimly lit party
where you sort of see that after Imaging
startled
uh just the flash of light you see that
floater
and so obviously pilots who are in
critical phases of flight
such as takeoff and Landing need
absolutely minimal distractions
and there have been some incidents where
the pilots themselves even when they're
not in critical phases have passed
through or flown into a laser beam uh or
been scanned by it momentarily and have
reacted uh poorly in other words
will say to the co-pilot hey look over
there there's a laser and they both look
in that direction and of course are
momentarily flash blinded disoriented
and there's been instances where Pilots
have rubbed their eyes at a very
severely and then gone and claimed that
they were damaged by the laser in actual
fact there was more damage from rubbing
their eyes and they just left them alone
so
the international laser display
Association in the states got together
with the SAG G10 people who are a
technical group responsible for advising
on rules and regulations and worked with
the cdrh in the states there's a similar
group of laserists here in Canada who
are currently working with the Canadian
government to improve the rules and the
way things are done and to make these
shows safer by doing things like having
spotters in some cases a couple hotels
in Las Vegas installed radar systems oh
my goodness if they at the uh an
aircraft should Transit the beam their
beam could be turned off so these uh
kinds of measures have been taken to
increase the safety but the biggest
thing that's not being done so far is
pilot education in other words Pilots
have hundreds of hours of simulator
training to handle every conceivable
kind of emergency but they're not
trained how to deal with a bright flash
of light so that is that is the
remaining area that needs to be worked
on so far we've been very fortunate that
there have been no serious incidents in
this regard but the industry overall is
very cognizant of of that kind of thing
and is taking measures to prevent
anything from happening do you need a
license to do any laser light show or
did that license kick into a certain
power
uh first of all it's country specific in
other words this varies from country to
Country in certain South American
countries the authorities go laser
what's that in other countries such as
the United States where your government
is very fond of extreme bureaucracy
large parts of paperwork that's indeed
what you face to make a general rule for
uh the United States anything under 4.9
milliwatts is quite is considered safe
and doesn't require any paperwork but as
soon as you use a five milliwatt or
greater laser in public then you're
required to have a variance for the
equipment which is something you have to
get from the cdrh division of the FDA no
if someone were to buy some laser
equipment they'd buy a five milliwatt
laser they buy a little bean scan unit
and they want to go out and they want to
do different parties and things with
that do they need a license and and to
kill paperwork for each one of those
jobs or just yes you need a site
variance for each place that
show plus you need a variance for the
equipment
what's happening with lasers in some of
the other fields well actually believe
it or not the hottest topic uh that
that's on the horizon is laser pointers
hmm
the UK recently banned outright the sale
of laser pointers oh really power yes uh
France is apparently looking into doing
the same thing and there's been a lot of
concern about this now back in the old
days when someone wanted to buy a laser
they would be looking at getting a
helium neon laser which requires a power
cord
cost a hundred or two hundred dollars
and you know as a 12 or 18 inch long
device and so therefore they were
particularly portable but now we live in
an age where we have these little laser
diode pens that you can buy at Business
Depot and Radio Shack and uh they put
out about five milliwatts of power and
people are using them at hockey games
and soccer games and concerts and so on
and they're becoming a downright
annoyance
the the most sensitive part of the human
body to the laser is the eye and just as
you can use a magnifying glass to focus
the Sun and burn something with it the
lens in the human eye also focuses a
laser beam into a very fine point on the
back of the eye so for example one
milliwatt going in based on the focusing
effect of the eye could produce an
energy density close to 10 000
milliwatts on the surface of the retina
it could burn the retina now there are a
lot of factors that enter into this
there's the blink aversion response
which means when a bright light hits
your eye you blink and you look away
the human eye doesn't actually ever
stand still it sort of differs even when
you're looking at something it moves
minutely up and down at all times to
keep the image moving on the rods and
cones at the back of the eye so in and
of themselves the laser pointer is not
likely to cause any eye damage
particularly when you've got a situation
where there's a person holding it in
their hand and another person several
feet away these are two human beings
human beings are not rigidly fixed in
space like buildings but it's an
annoyance
it's rude
and it's very distracting and you can
have uh situations where people get
distracted at critical times or if you
have say a sports event and there have
been reports of this happening where
there are 50 or 60 people in the crowd
all pointing laser pointers at the same
place it becomes very annoying and
difficult for whomever those pointers
are being pointed at to get on with
whatever they're supposed to be doing so
I suspect that we will probably see more
rigid enforcement in in North America of
sales of laser pointers and I think that
it behooves people who use them to be
responsible in what they do and not
Point them in anyone's face